今天我想谈谈 Go 语言
today I'd like to talk about Go which
它真的相当有趣
is interesting especially interesting
在这门课中
for us in this course because course Go
未来的 labs
is the language at the labs you're all
将使用 Go 语言来完成，所以今天我想
going to do the labs in and so I want to
特别是在
the labs and in most particular to
分布式程序中，嗯，首先
distributed programming um first of all
为什么在这门课里我们要使用 Go 语言？
you know it's worth asking why we use go
事实上，我们已经使用过
in this class in fact we could have used
其它风格的编程语言
any one of a number of other system
非常多，比如
style languages plenty languages like
Java, C#, 甚至是 Python
Java or C sharp or even Python that
这些语言提供了我们需要的工具
provide the kind of facilities we need
我们也在这门课用使用过 C++
and indeed we used to use C++ in this
供你使用
particularly convenient
尤其是在多线程
that's good support for threads and
锁，以及线程间同步上，Go 都做的相当的棒！
locking and synchronization between
未来我们会大量使用这些特性
threads which we use a lot it is a
另外 RPC package(RPC 包)也相当的方便
convenient remote procedure call package
它听起来好像没什么大不了的
which doesn't sound like much but it
但是这在其它诸如 C++ 这样的语言中
actually turns out to be a significant
真的是个很大的包袱，用起来不尽人意
constraint from many languages like C++
比如说，你很难找到一个
for example it's actually a bit hard to
方便好用的 RPC 包
find a convenient easy to use remote
当然了
procedure call package and of course we
在这门课里或是
use it all the time in this course or
程序中，并且在不同的机器上，我们会用它做比较
programs and different machines to talk
不像 C++, Go 是类型安全
to each other unlike C++ go is type safe
它总是或多或少存在和内存相关的 bug
scribbles over some random piece of
然后导致程序产生一些奇奇怪怪的事情
memory and then causes the program to do
然而，Go 的垃圾回收机制
mysterious things and that just
能尽可能的帮我们消灭大量类似的 bug
eliminates a big class of bugs similarly
这意味着
it's garbage collected which means you
你再也不用身处 double free 的危险之中
never in danger of priam the same memory
也不用再为释放正在被使用的内存而担忧
twice or free memory that's still in use
还有一些不用的 vector
or something the garbage vector just
当它不被使用时，也应该要被释放掉
frees things when they stop being used
还有一些看起来不太明显的问题
and one thing it's maybe not obvious
直到你接触
until you played around with just this
这样的程序之前
kind of programming before but the
多线程协同，垃圾回收
combination of threads and garbage
也是相当重要的事情之一
collection is particularly important one
在非垃圾回收型语言中
of the things that goes wrong in a non
这些都很容易出错，比如 C++
garbage collected language like C++ if
如果你使用它(C++)编写多线程程序
you use threads is that it's always a
它总会出现一些让人迷惑的的问题
bit of a puzzle and requires a bunch of
这要求你需要一大本草稿本帮助你去理解
bookkeeping to figure out when the last
什么时候最后一个线程
thread
不在使用共享对象
that's using a shared object has
因为只有
finished using that object because only
在这个时候，你才能释放对象
then can you free the object and so you end
所以最终你会写很多代码
up writing quite a bit of code just like
就像许多程序员会
many of the programmer writes about a
自己动手写一堆代码那样
bunch of code manually. you know do
你知道可以实现类似引用计数这样的功能
reference counting or something in order
来解决它，你也知道
to figure out you know when the last
如果有垃圾回收，这些问题都将不复存在
completely goes away if you use garbage
比如在 Go 语言中
collection like we have in go
最后一点，这门语言比 C++ 要简单的多。
and finally the language is simple much
使用 C++ 的麻烦的问题之一，比如
simpler than C++ one of the problems
你可能只是一个拼写错误
with using C++ is that often if you made
它就可能导致编译器
an error you know maybe even just a typo
报出非常复杂的错误信息
the the error message you get back from
在 C++ 里
the compiler is so complicated that in
尝试去理解这些
C++ it's usually not worth trying to
错误信息不太值得了
figure out what the error message meant
我觉得更好、更快的方法
and I find it's always just much quicker
就是去看看出错的那一行代码
to go look at the line number and try to
尝试去猜测它到底是什么错误
guess what the error must have been
因为这门语言真是太复杂了
because the language is far too complicated
然而 Go，你懂的
whereas go is you know probably doesn't
它没有许多让人热衷的特性
have a lot of people's favorite features
相对而言它是一门“直接了当”的语言
but it's relatively straightforward
Okay, 所以现在你们
language okay so at this point you're
都应该看看 Go 语言教程
both on the tutorial if you're looking
如果你正在纠结关于这门语言
for sort of you know what to look at
你下一步应该学习什么的时候
next to learn about the language a good
有一个好东西你可以看看
place to look is the document titled
名为《Effective Go》
effective go which you know you can find
你可以通过互联网搜索到这本书
by searching the web
好吧，现在我们谈谈多线程
all right the first thing I want to talk about is threads
在这门课里
the reason why we care a lot about
实现并发的重要工具
be using to manage concurrency in
在分布式程序中
programs and concurrency is a particular
并发相当有意思
interest in distributed programming
比较常见的情况是
because it's often the case that one
一个程序需要同时
program actually needs to talk to a
和多台计算机通信
bunch of other computers you know client
客户端可能会同时和多台服务器通信
may talk to many servers or a server may
一台服务器可能会同时响应
be serving requests at the same time on
来自不同客户端的多条请求
behalf of many different clients and so
我们需要一种方式来解释
we need a way to say oh you know I'm my
客户端在通信
seven different clients and I want a
我想要一种简单的方式
simple way to allow it to do these seven
实现它能同时做 7 件不同的事情
different things you know without too
我不需要做太复杂的编程
much complex programming I mean sort of
线程就能很好的解决它
thrust threads are the answer so these
在 Go 的文档中
are the things that the go documentation
它把线程称为 goroutine
calls go routines which I call threads
goroutine 真的很像
the go routines are really this same
大家所说的线程
as what everybody else calls threads
你可以这样来思考线程
so the way to think of threads is
你有一个程序
that you have a program，one program
有一个地址空间，让我来画个小盒子
and one address space I'm gonna draw a
串行执行的程序是没有多个线程的
serial program without threads you just
你只有一个线程
have one thread of execution executing
在一个多线程程序中，比方说 Go 程序
in a threaded program like a go program you could have
你可以拥有多个线程，
multiple threads and you know I got raw
我来画些弯弯的线条来表示它
it as multiple squiggly lines and when
每条线之间都是分开的
each line represents really is a
尤其是
separate if the especially if the
如果这些线程同时执行
threads are executing at the same time
那它们就分别有一个属于自己的程序计数器
but a separate program counter a
一套寄存器和一个栈
separate set of registers and a separate
是的，每个线程都有自己的一套东西
stack for each of the threads so that
自己的一套线程控制
they can have a sort of their own thread
他们可以在程序中不同的部分
of control and be executing each thread
执行每个线程
in a different part of the program and
有一个不太让人注意的细节
so hidden here is that for every stack
每一个独立的线程都有一个栈
there's a seprate thread there's a
线程会在这些栈上执行
stack that it's executing on
这些栈都在程序中的同一个地址空间里
the stacks are actually in in the one address space
所以，即使
of the program so even though each stack
每个线程都有它自己的栈
each thread has its own stack
严格来讲他们都在同一地址空间中
technically the they're all in the same
如果知道正确的地址的话
address space and different threads
不同的线程之间
could refer to each other stacks if they
是可以互相访问的他们的栈的
knew the right addresses
当你首次启动程序时
you first start up the program and it
它会在 main 函数中运行
runs in main that's also it's just a go
它就是一个 goroutine，然后做完所有的事情
routine and can do all the things that goroutine can do
好啦
all right so as I
我想说的最重要的原因
mentioned one of the big reasons is
就是允许程序中不同的部分
to allow different parts of the program to
我常常说 IO 并发是出于历史原因
that as IO concurrency for historical
称之为 IO 并发
reasons and the reason I call it IO
你可能有一个线程
oh you might have one thread that's waiting to
正在等待从磁盘上读数据
read from the disk and while it's waiting to
当它在等待的时候，你又想要
reach from the disk you'd like to have a
另一个线程，可能用来做计算或是
second thread that maybe can compute or
所以 IO 并发
and so I/O concurrency is one of
也是你使用多线程的地方之一
the things that threads by you for us it
比如说
would usually mean I can I/O concurrency
我们有一个程序
we usually mean I can have one program
这就是我们要解决的问题
that's how it'll come up for us
每个线程
you wanted to launch that thread would have code
都会通过 RPC 发送 request 消息
that you know sent the remote procedure call request message
然后在这个位置等待
and sort of waited at this point in the thread
当响应回复时
and then finally when the reply came
这个线程将会继续执行
back the thread would continue executing
使用多线程
and using threads allows us to have
可以让我们同时发起多个网络请求
multiple threads that all launch requests into the network at the same time
所有线程都会等待回复
they all wait or they don't have to
也不是非得在同一时间去发请求
do it at the same time they can you know
我就写并行化吧
which I'll just call parallelism
我们想通过线程来达到并行化的目的
and here the thing where we'd be trying to achieve with threads
并行化就是如果你有个多核机器
is if you have a multi-core
我确定你们每个人都能用你自己的电脑做到
machine like I'm sure all of you do in
如果你有一个计算繁重的工作
your laptops if you have a sort of
它需要消耗许多 CPU 时钟
compute heavy job that needs a lot of
这不是太好
CPU cycles wouldn't it be nice if you
比方说它是用 Go 写的多线程程序
machine and indeed if you write a multi-threaded go
比如一直在那执行一个循环，计算 pi（圆周率)的值
loop and you know compute digits of pi
直到达到机器上 cpu 核的极限
or something then up to the limit of the number of cores in the physical machine
你的线程将会真正的以并行的方式运行
your threads will run truly in parallel
如果你启动 2 个线程代替 1 个线程
and if you launch you know two threads
你就能获得 2 倍的性能
instead of one you'll get twice as many
就能使用 2 倍数量的 CPU 核时钟
you'll be able to use twice as many CPU cycles per second
这其实没什么大不了的
deal on this course
我们并不会把多过精力
be... it's rare that we'll sort of think
放在这一类并行化上
specifically about this kind of parallelism
在现实世界中
in the real world though of
我们开发像服务器这样的程序
building things like servers to form
来组成分布式系统的一部分
parts of the distributed systems it can
有时让服务器
sometimes be extremely important to be
能使用多线程
able to have the server be able to run
能使用多核还是非常重要的
threads and harness the CPU power of a
因为往往客户端
lot of cores just because the load from
带给服务器的负载非常高
clients can often be pretty high
okay, 所以并行化是第二个原因
okay so parallelism is a second reason
那么为什么咱们会在分布式系统中
why threads are quite a bit interested in
如此关注多线程呢
distributed systems and a third reason
第三个原因，但也可能不那么重要
which is maybe a little bit less
就是有时候
important is there's some there's times
你只是想在后台做一些事情
when you really just want to be able to do something in the background
比如你就想周期性的去执行它
or you know there's just something you need to do periodically
但你又不愿意在主线程
and you don't want to have to sort of in the main part of your
插入一些检查
program sort of insert checks to say
比如我要做的那个动作
well should I be doing this things that
每秒都能做
up that every second does whatever the
这里有个例子
and an example which will come up for you
也是经常会遇到的情况
is it's often the case
比如有一个 master 服务需要
that some you know a master server may want to
周期性的检查它的 worker 服务是否一直存活
check periodically whether its workers are still alive because one
因为这些 worker 之一宕机的话
of them is died you know you want to
就需要把工作扔到另一台机器上去执行
launch that work on another machine like
就像 MapReduce 那样
MapReduce might do that and one way to
你可以每秒、每分钟
arrange sort of oh do this check every
通过发送一条“你还活着吗？”这样的消息到 worker 服务上
second every minute you know send a message to the worker are you alive is
你能启动一个 goroutine
to fire off a go routine that just sits
然后执行一个死循环，sleep 1 秒后
in a loop that sleeps for a second and
然后做需要周期执行的动作
then does the periodic thing and then
然后又 sleep 1 秒
sleeps for a second again and so in the
在后面的 lab 里，你最后将会创建这样的线程
labs you'll end up firing off these kind of threads quite a bit
（提问...猜测是开启 goroutine 开销的问题）
yes is the
这个开销是值得的，是的，这个开销
overhead worth it yes the overhead is
真的非常少
really pretty small for this stuff I
这依赖于你创建多少线程
mean you know it depends on how many you
但是如果你创建了 100 万个线程
create a million threads that he sit in
这可能会给你的机器带来巨大的负载
probably a huge load on your machine but
如果你就创建了 10 个线程的话
if you create you know ten threads that
sleep 1 秒，然后做一点点工作
sleep for a second and do a little bit
这真的没什么大不了的
of work it's probably not a big deal at all
功能搞到一起
together they're different different
放在一行代码里
activities into one line of code it's
它只会消耗一点点 CPU
it's worth the small amount of CPU cost almost always
如果很不幸
still you know you will if
你在 Labs 发现
you're unlucky you'll discover in the
有些循环 sleep 的时间不够长
labs that some loop of yours is not
或者是创建了大量的 goroutine
sleeping long enough or are you fired
也从未让他们退出
off a bunch of these and never made them
这样 goroutine 就会越来越多
exit for example and they just
甚至是你做的更过火
accumulate so you can push it too far
okay，所以这些原因
okay so these are the reasons that the
是人们喜欢线程的主要原因
main reasons that people like threads a
也是我们在这门课里使用多线程的原因
lot and that will use threads in this
关于线程大家还有什么问题吗？
class any other questions about threads
（提问：...）通过异步编程
in general by asynchronous program you
你的意思是通过单线程
mean like a single thread of control
来追踪不同活动的状态是吗？
that keeps state about many different
yeah，这真的是个好问题
activities yeah so this is a good question actually
如果不使用多线程会怎样？
there is you know what would happen if we didn't have threads
你知道服务器
that could you know a server
能够同时与不同客户端通信
that could talk to many different clients at the same time
或是客户端能同时与多个服务器通信
or a client that could talk to many servers right
这时候应该使用什么样的工具？
what what tools could be used and it
你可以使用事件驱动编程
so sort of or you could use event-driven
事件驱动编程的一般结构
programming and the the general structure of an event-driven program is
通常它有一个线程
usually that it has a single thread and
同时有一个循环
a single loop and what that loop does is
这个循环等待输入
sits there and waits for any input or
或者是其它任何事件
sort of any event that might trigger
这些事件能触发程序继续进行
processing so an event might be the
事件可能是一个来自客户端的请求
arrival of a request from a client or a
可能是定时器到期，如果你在编写
timer going off or if you're building a
windows 系统程序
Windows System, many Windows
你电脑上的许多 windows 系统程序
systems on your laptops I've driven
或者是鼠标移动这样的事件
or Mouse move
因此你可能会有一个单一的
or something so you might have a single
只有一个控制线程的程序
an event-driven programing of a
这个线程有一个循环一直等待输入
single thread of control sits a loop
无论何时有输入进来
waits for input and whenever it gets an
比如收到报文，它能够找出来
input like a packet it figures out oh
是哪个客户端发送的这个报文
you know which client did this packet
它有一张表格
come from and then it'll have a table of
记录这个客户端到底处于什么样的活动状态
sort of what the state is of whatever activity its managing for that client
比如说，oh 上帝，
and it'll say oh gosh I was in the
我现在处于“读”某个文件的状态
middle of reading such-and-such a file
那么它就会要求我去读下一个数据块
you know now it's asked me to read the
然后我就会去读取下一个数据块然后返回
next block I'll go and be the next block
使用线程的话
and return it and threads are generally
通常会变的更加方便
more convenient because they allow you
计算，然后发送消息，然后等待响应
computes sends a message waits for
这种编程模式的问题在于
that said they are and so one problem with
它实现起来有点痛苦
the scheme is that it's it's a little bit of a pain to program
另一个潜在的缺陷
another potential defect is that while you get
当你用这种方法获取了 IO 并发后
io concurrency from this approach you
你就没法利用 CPU 的并行化机制
don't get CPU parallelism so if you're
所以当你写一个负载很高的服务
writing a busy server that would really
你得相方设法把一台大型机器的 32 核都用上
like to keep you know 32 cores busy on a big server machine
使用一个单一循环的话，你知道，它相当的不自然
you know a single loop is you know it's it's not a very
也很难获得多核的性能
natural way to harness more than one core
通常换来的性能提升相比多线程来说并不会太多
quite a bit less than threads you know
而且线程相对来说也很廉价
threads are pretty cheap but each one of
但是每个线程都有一个栈
these threads is sitting on a stack you
栈通常是 1kb 或数千字节
know stack is a kilobyte or a kilobytes
如果你有 20 个线程
or something you know if you have 20 of
这些消耗根本不用在意
these threads who cares if you have a
但是你若有 100 万个线程
million of these threads then it's
它是指下一步应该选择哪个线程运行
bookkeeping for deciding what the thread to run next might also start you know
通常有一个调度列表，上面记录了 1000 个线程
you now have list scheduling lists with a thousand threads in them
这时候切换线程执行将付出相当昂贵的代价
the threads can start to get quite expensive so if
所以，当你只有一个服务器的时候
you are in a position where you need to
你的服务器需要为 100 万个客户端提供服务
have a single server that serves you know a million clients
你需要为这 100 万个客户端记录一些状态
and has to sort of keep a little bit of state for each of a million clients
这个代价还是挺高的
this could be expensive
一个简单的而又五脏俱全高性能的服务
efficient low overhead service in event-driven programming
就是你需要多做点工作
just a lot more work
你是问我 JavaScript 吗？
are you asking my JavaScript I
有人知道吗? 这得取决于具体实现
your does anybody know depends on the implementation
yeah，不过我确实不太清楚这个
yeah so I don't know
有个很自然的想法
I mean it's a natural thought though even
即使是在 Go 中
in you know even in Go you might well
假设你知道你的机器有 8 个核
want to have if you knew your machine
你想写一个世界上最高效的 server
had eight cores if you wanted to write
你可能就会启动 8 个线程
the world's most efficient whatever server you could fire up eight threads
每个线程上运行一个精简的事件驱动循环
and on each of the threads run sort of stripped-down event-driven loop
一个循环一个核
just you know sort of one event loop per core and
对于 IO 并发来说，这是一种获得并行化的方式
that you know that would be a way to get both parallelism and to the I/O concurrency concurrency
(提问)
yes
通常，对于类 UNIX 系统的机器来说
so usually on a like a UNIX machine a
一个进程就是一个单独运行的程序
process is a single program that you're
只有一个地址空间
running and a sort of single address
一大片可供进程使用的内存
space a single bunch of memory for the
在这个进程里你可能同时会有好多个线程
process and inside a process you might have multiple threads
当你准备好一个 go 程序并运行
and when you ready a go program and you run the go program
将会创建一个 unix 进程和一块内存区
running the go program creates one unix process and one sort of memory area
当你的 Go 进程创建 goroutine 时
and then when your go process creates go
它们实际上都是在同一个进程里的
routines those are so sitting inside that one process
我不太确定真实的答案是不是这样
so I'm not sure that's really an answer but just historically
但历史上，操作系统都提供了像这样的大盒子
the operating systems have provided like
它就是个进程
this big box is the process that's
实际上这也取决于操作系统的实现
implemented by the operating system and
也不关心你使用什么语言
your process what language you use none
不关心操作系统内部的业务逻辑
of the operating systems business but
在进程内部能运行多个线程就行了
inside that process you can run lots of
好，如果在你的机器上运行了不止一个进程
threads now you know if you run more than one process in your machine you know you run more than one program
比如一个编辑器或是编译器
like an editor or compiler
操作系统需要让它们彼此分开
the operating system keep quite separate
你的编辑器和你的编译器
right you're your editor and your compiler each have
都有自己的内存空间
memory but it's not the same memory that
他们之间无法看到彼此的内存
are not allowed to look at each other
但是在同一个进程中，线程与线程之间可以共享内存
one program the threads can share memory
可以使用 channel(Go语言中的概念) 进行同步
and can synchronize with channels and
也可以使用 mutex 等
use mutexes etc. but between
但进程之间是没有交集的
processes there's just no no interaction
这类软件的传统结构就是这样
that's just a traditional structure of these this kind of software
(提问)
yeah
你只有一个单核机器
single core machine that's really only
这意味着在同一个时刻你只能做一件事情
running and as just doing one thing at a
你这样想
time maybe the right way to think about
你打算在你的机器上运行多进程
it is that you're going to be you're running multiple processes on your machine
操作系统把 CPU 时间片
the operating system will give
反复的分配给这两个程序
the CPU sort of time slicing back and forth between these two programs
当硬件时钟到期时
so when the hardware timer ticks and the
操作系统就判断是时候把 CPU 从当前正在运行的进程剥夺
operating systems decides it's time to take away the CPU from the currently running process
然后把 CPU 分配给另一个进程
and give it to another
这件事件是在进程级别上做的
process that's done at a process level
这有点复杂，好
it's complicated all right let me let me
让我们重新再思考这个问题
let me restart this these the threads
操作系统是知道这一切的
the threads that it knows about so in a
所以操作系统可能会清楚
situation like this the operating system
这儿有两个线程在这个进程中，有三个线程在那个进程
might know that there are two threads here in this process and three threads in this process
当时钟到期时
and when the timer ticks
操作系统会基于一些调度算法选择一个不同的线程来运行
the operating system will based on some scheduling algorithm pick a different thread thread to run
在这个进程中的线程和另一进程中的线程可能是不同的
it might be a different thread in this process or one of the threads in this process
另外，Go 会聪明复用一个操作系统线程
in addition go cleverly multiplex as
在上面运行尽可能多的 goroutine 以节省开支
many go routines on top of single operating system threads to reduce overhead
所以这可能需要两个阶段去调度
so it's really probably a two
首先操作系统选择一个线程去运行
stages of scheduling the operating system picks which big thread to run
然后在这个进程中，Go 会再去选择哪个 goroutine 去运行
and then within that process go may have a choice of go routines to run
好啦，线程真的很方便
all right okay so threads are convenient
大多数时候，使用它
because a lot of times they allow you to write the code for each thread
然而，事实上写多线程程序是有些挑战的
however there are in fact some challenges with writing threaded code
其中一个是共享数据
one is what to do about shared data one
如果某个线程在内存中创建了一个对象
if one thread creates an object
在其它线程中你也能使用它
in memory you can let other threads use
你可以创建个数组或是别的什么东西
it right you can have a array or
所有不同的线程都能读写
something that all the different threads are reading and writing and that
这就存在一些临界情况
sometimes critical right if you you know
首先它会先查一下缓存中的数据
client request it's gonna first look in
但是这个共享缓存，每个线程都能读
that cache but the shared cache and each
当线程里有新的信息时
thread reads it and the threads may write the cache to update it
线程可能会向缓存里写入数据进行更新
when they have new information to stick in the cache
所以这真的很厉害
so it's really cool you can share
你可以共享内存
that memory but it turns out that it's
但是事实也表明这也非常容易出现 bug
very very easy to get bugs if you're not
如果你不关心多线程之间共享内存的话
careful and you're sharing memory between threads
有个经典的例子
so a totally classic example is you know supposing your
假设你有一个全局变量 N
thread so you have a global variable N
在不同的线程之间共享
and that's shared among the different
其中一个线程只是对 N 做自增
threads and a thread just wants to
这可能就是造成 bug 的原因
increment n right but itself this is likely to be an invitation to bugs right
如果你不做一些特殊处理的话
if you don't do anything special around this code
为什么？
and the reason is that you
无论何时你在多线程中读写共享数据
know whenever you write code in a thread that you you know is accessing reading or writing data that's shared with other
总是存在一种可能性
threads you know there's always the
你得牢记
possibility and you got to keep in mind
在同一时刻，总有其它的线程可能也正在查看
that some other thread may be looking at the data
所以这里有个很明显的问题
so the obvious problem with
看这里，线程 1 正在执行
this is that maybe thread 1 is executing this code and thread 2 is actually
但是另一个不同的线程 2 也在执行相同的代码
in the same function in a different thread executing the very same code
而是由编译器吐出来的机器码
code you're running machine code the compiler produced and
机器码长啥样呢
what that machine code does is it you
首先把 X 载入到一个寄存器里
know it loads X into a register
然后给寄存器的加 1
you know adds one to the register and
接着再把寄存器的值保存到 X
then stores that register into X with
都在执行这行代码
they're both executing this line of code
他们都会执行 load x 到寄存器
you know they both load the variable X
然后他们都给寄存器加 1
they both increment that register so
这样所有线程各有自的寄存器的值是 1
they get one and they both store one
最后再把寄存器的值 1 重新保存到内存里
back to memory and now two threads of
但是碰巧这样写并不正确
the programmer wanted but chances are
碰巧程序想要的结果不是 1
not right chances are the programmer wanted to not 1
(提问...) 有一些指令是原子的
no, some some instructions
这个问题不错
are atomic so the question is a very
这些独立的指令是不是原子的
good question which it's whether individual instructions are atomic
答案是有些是，有些不是
so the answer is some are and some aren't
对于 32 位的 store 指令它极有可能是原子的
so a store a 32-bit store is likely the extremely likely to be atomic
从某种意义上来说，如果有两个处理器
in the sense that if 2 processors store
最终要么是其中一个处理器上的 32 位值
well you'll end up with is either the 32 bits
要么是另一个处理器上的 32 位值
from one processor or the 32 bits from the other processor
而不是一个混合的值
but not a mixture
其它尺寸大小的未必就这么简单
other sizes it's not so clear like one byte stores it depends on
比如一个字节的存储这依赖于你所使用的 CPU
the CPU you using because a one byte
因为 1 字节的存储几乎和 32 字节的 load 差不多
store is really almost certainly a 32
就是 8 bit 的修改，和一个 32 字节的存储
byte load and then a modification of 8 bits and a 32 byte store
这依赖于处理器和更复杂的指令
but it depends on the processor and more complicated instructions
比如微处理器上的自增指令
like increment your microprocessor may well have an increment instruction
它能直接给内存上某个地址的值加 1
that can directly increment some memory location like
未必就是原子的
pretty unlikely to be atomic although
尽管这些指令存在原子版本的
there's atomic versions of some of these instructions
好，咱们继续。所以这是一个非常经典的错误
so there's no. any way all right so this is this is a just classic danger
通常我们叫他“竞争”(注：后面不译，直接使用 race)，后面我打算会多次提起它
and it's usually called a race I'm gonna come up a lot
因为你将会做大量的多线程编程
cause you're gonna do a lot of
且存在共享状态
threaded programming with shared state
这里 race 这个词
race I think refers to as some ancient
我认为来源于电子电路中的一类古老的 bug
class of bugs involving electronic circuits
但是对我们来说
but for us that you know the reason
称为 race 是因为如果一个 CPU 已经开始执行这段代码
why it's called a race is because if one of the CPUs have started
另一些线程正在结束这段代码
executing this code and the other one the others thread is sort of getting close to this code
这就是 race
it's sort of a race
如果第一个处理器的 store
if the first processor actually
第二个处理器将 load 值 1，然后再加 1，再把 2 存入
value and the second processor will load one and add one to it in store two
好了，你可以通过上面这种方式理解这个术语
that's how you can justify this terminology
okay, 解决这个问题的方式很简单
okay and so the way you solve this certainly something this simple
加个锁就行了
is you insert locks
你知道，作为一个程序员
you know you as a programmer you have
你心中应该有一些办法如何给数据加锁
some strategy in mind for locking the
只有在持有锁的时候，这个共享数据才能被使用
data you can say well you know this piece of shared data can only be used when such-and-such a lock is held and
Go 调用 lock 来锁住 mutex，你能看到 mu.Lock()
mutexes so what you'll see is a mu dot lock
加在这一段使用共享数据的代码前面
before a sequence of code that uses
然后在结束的地方调用  mu.Unlock()
shared data and you unlock afterwards
然后执行所有这些代码
gets to do all this stuff
在结束之前，另一个线程都不能继续
and finish before the other one is allowed to proceed
你可以考虑把这些在锁中间的代码封装起来
and so you can think of wrapping a some code in a lock
就像这一堆东西
as making a bunch of you know remember
(提问)
yes
你是……胆子小吗，能不能再说一遍？
should you sissy can you repeat the question
实际上三个不同变量
different variables and the answer is
所以答案是 go 并不知道
that go has no idea it's not there's no
它是个 mutex
mutex there's just there's no
在 lock 和任何变量之间
association in the language between the
他们并没有什么关联
lock and any variables the associations
在程序员脑袋中
in the programmers head so as a
你只需要说
programmer you need to say oh here's a
oh, 这里有一堆共享数据
bunch of shared data and any time you
在任意时刻，你修改其中任意一个
modify any of it you know here's a
有些复杂的数据结构
complex data structure say a tree or an
比如是树或是可扩展的 hash 表或是别的什么
expandable hash table or something
任何时候你若打算修改它
anytime you're going to modify it and of
当然，树是有许多对象组合而成的
course a tree is composed many many
任何时候，你打算修改任何
objects anytime you got to modify
和这个数据结构关联的东西
anything that's associated with this
你都得先拿到这样的锁
data structure you have to hold such and
当然，包含许多对象
such a lock. and of course, many
以及对象的集合的修改
objects and the set of objects changes
因为你可能会分配一个新的树节点
because you might allocate new tree
但是程序员必须想出一个策略
nodes but it's really the programmer who
保证在同一时刻
sort of works out a strategy for
数据结构只在一个核上被使用
ensuring that the data structure is used
所以
by only one core at a time and so it
需要创建一个甚至是多个锁
creates the one or maybe more locks and
有许多许多加锁的方案
there's many many locking strategies you
程序员可以制定一些策略来分配锁
programmer works out the strategy
在脑子里记住数据之间关系
allocates the locks and keeps in the programmers head the relationship to the data
但是对 Go 来说
but go for go it's this is this
这里的这个锁其实非常简单
lock it's just like a very simple thing
它是一个锁对象
there's a lock object the first thread
第一个线程调用 lock 方法拿到锁
that calls lock gets the lock other
其它所有线程等待直接 unlock 被执行
threads have to wait until unlocks
所有这些事情 Go 都清楚
and that's all go knows
(提问)
yeah
不用给一个对象中
does it not lock all variables that are
当你请求锁的时候
variables and locks so when you acquire
当你的代码调用 lock 方法时
that lock when you have code that calls
它在做什么
lock exactly what it is doing it is
它就是想拿到这个锁，这就是它的作用
acquiring this lock and that's all this
其它任何人想尝试获得锁对象
does and anybody else who tries to lock
所以在某个地方
objects so somewhere else who would have
需要声明一个 mutex mu;
declared you know mutex mu all right
这个 mu 指向了某些特别的 lock 对象
and this mu refers to some particular
有许多（听不懂。。。）
lock object and there are many many
所有这些动作都是获取这把锁
locks right all this does is acquires
其它任何人想获得它
this lock and anybody else who wants to
完全由我们自己决定
programmers what we were protecting with
(提问) 所以问题是
that lock so the question is is it
我们假设有个城市的分区图
like supposing it a zoning map yeah and
你可能希望，尽管这不是真的
you know you would hope although it's
地图内部需要有一把锁来保护它
not true that map internally would have
这是个合理的策略
a lock protecting it and that's a reasonable strategy
有了这些会怎样？
would be to have them, I mean what would be to have them if you
如果你定义了一个
define a data structure that needs to be
需要加锁使用的数据结构
locked to have the lock be sort of
这个锁是内部私有的
interior that have each of the data
数据结构的每个方法都有责任
structures methods be responsible for
请求这把锁
acquiring that lock and the user the
用户，数据结构可能永远都不知道有这把锁的存在
data structure may never know that
这个相当合理
that's pretty reasonable and the only
但是唯一点需要打破
point at which that breaks down is that
好吧，有几件事，其中之一是
um well it's a couple things one is if
因为他们得多付出锁的开销
they were paying the lock overhead for
他们清楚这没必要加锁
something they knew didn't need to be
所以这是个潜在的问题
locked so that's one potential problem
另一件事
the other is that if you if there's any
但常规解决死锁的方法
but the usual solutions to deadlocks
需要把锁拿到实现的外面来
requires lifting the locks out of out of
放到调用代码的地方（注：把函数里面的锁，移到外面）
the implementations up into the calling
这是个不太好的方法
the locks but it's not always a good
okay, 所以你使用多线程的问题之一
idea all right okay so one problem you
同时访问数据的加锁策略
strategy for making access to the data single thread one thread at a time or
另一个方案是你可以让你的代码不要共享数据
you fix your code to not share data
如果可以的话，这种方法会更好
if you can do that it's that's probably
因为这会降低复杂性
better because it's less complex all
好，现在来看另一个话题 coordination(协作)
right so another issue that shows up
可能并不知道其它线程也在加锁
probably have no idea that the other ones exist
他们只是想在没有人干涉的情况下拿到数据
they just want to like be able to get out the data without anybody else interfering
但也有一些情况
but there are also cases
你确实就是故意的想让不同的线程之间
where you need where you do
互相受到制约
intentionally want different threads to
我就是想等着你
interact I want to wait for you
比如你生产某些数据
maybe you're producing some data you
但是你又和我不是同一个线程
know you're a different thread than me
你生产数据
you're you're producing data I'm gonna
我想在你生产完数据前一直等待
wait until you've generated the data
直到你完成后，我再去读取
before I read it right or you launch a
或者是你启动了一堆线程去抓取 web 页面
bunch of threads to say you crawl the
然后需要等待所有线程都执行结束
web and you want to wait for all those
所以当我们想
fits to finish so there's times when we
特意的互相等待的时候
intentionally want different to us to interact with each other to wait for each other
这种情况通常就称为 coordination (协作)
and that's usually called coordination
你要是做完了咱们的教程的话
and there's a bunch of as you probably
就能知道很多了
know from having done the tutorial
Go 中有很多技术可以做到
there's a bunch of techniques in go for
比如 channel (通道)
doing this like channels
比如有个东西叫 condition variables (条件变量)
like there's a idea called condition
这东西很牛逼
variables which is great if there's some
如果有些线程在那里等着（马儿不走了）
thread out there and you want to kick it
你想周期性的“踢”它一下（类似马儿，抽它一下）
period you're not sure if the other
但你不确定哪些线程是否正在等待你
threads even waiting for you but if it
如果它在等你，你就踢它一下
is waiting for you you just like to give
这样它就知道它需要
it a kick so it can well know that it
继续做它应该要做的事情
should continue whatever it's doing and
还有一个工具 WaitGroup
then there's wait group which is
相当牛逼
particularly good for launching a a
常用于启动已知数据的 goroutine
known number of go routines and then
然后等待它们结束
waiting for them end off to finish and a
有时你运行到线程中的某个位置
that you sometimes run into where one thread
这个线程（T1)正在等待另外一个线程(T2)生产的数据
you know thread this thread is waiting for thread 2 to produce something so
我来画个箭头
you know it's draw an arrow to say
表示 T1 正在等待 T2
thread one is waiting for thread 2 you
线程 T1 可能正在等待 T2 释放锁
know for example thread one may be waiting for thread two to release a lock
或是向 channel 上发数据
or to send something on the channel or
又或是等着 T2 给 WaitGroup 计数减 1
to you know decrement something in a
然而不幸的是
wait group however unfortunately maybe T
T2 也可能正在等着 T1 做一些事情
two is waiting for thread thread one to
T2 在请求锁 B
acquire lock B so thread one is
应该这样，T1 持有锁 A, T2 持有锁 B
acquired lock A thread two is aquired
然后下一步，T1 也需要请求锁 B
lot B and then next thread one needs to
它需要同时持有 2 把锁
lock B also that is hold two locks which sometimes shows up
刚好 T2 也需要请求锁 A
and it just so happens that thread two needs to hold
这就死锁了
lock A that's a deadlock all right at
这至少需要他们都能抢到第一把锁
least grab their first lock and then
然后继续执行到他们需要第二把锁的位置
proceed down to where they need their
现在它们都在永远互相等待着对方
second lock and now they're waiting for
它们都无法继续进行下去
each other forever right neither can
也没有人能释放掉刚拿到的锁
proceed neither then can release the
通常什么都不会发生
lock and usually just nothing happens so
所以如果你的程序像机器一样停下来
if your program just kind of grinds to a
什么也不干的时候
halt and doesn't seem to be doing
okay，让我们看看教程里的 web 爬虫
okay all right let's look at the web crawler from the tutorial
这是一个使用多线程的例子
as an example of some of this threading stuff I have a
我这里有 2 种不同风格的方案
couple of two solutions in different
呃，实际上应该是有 3 种
styles are really three solutions in
不同风格的方案里
different styles to allow us to talk a
咱们可以谈谈多线程编程里的一些细节
bit about the details of some of this
首先
thread programming so first of all you
你们可能知道
all probably know web crawler its job is
爬虫就是你给它一个 URL 让它开始运行
you give it the URL of a page that it
在 web 页面里
starts at and you know many web pages
包含有许多链接指向了其它的页面
have links to other pages so what a web
所以 web 爬虫要做的就是
crawler is trying to do is if that's the
把这些链接指向的页面提取出来
first page extract all the URLs that were mentioned that pages links
然后继续抓取这些 url 指向的页面
those but all urls that they refer to
它应该要能够停止
and keep on going until it's fetched all
比如直到 web 中所有的页面被抓取完
the pages in the web let's just say and
另外
then it should stop in addition the the
网页构成的 graph 和 URL 存在环
graph of pages and URLs is cyclic that
如果你不关心的话
is if you're not careful
um 你的爬虫可能会结束
um you may end up following if you don't
你的爬虫永远无法结束
your crawler will never finish so one of
所以爬虫的工作之一就是需要记住
the jobs of the crawler is to remember
它抓取过的页面
the set of pages that is already crawled
或是已经开始抓取的页面
or already even started a fetch for and
对于任何正在抓取中的页面
to not start a second fetch for any page
都不应该有第二次抓取
that it's already started fetching on
你可以想象
and you can think of that as sort of
它是一个树结构
imposing a tree structure finding a sort
这个树结构是一个
of tree shaped subset of the cyclic
包含了环的实际网页 graph 的子集
graph of actual web pages okay so we
我们想避开环
want to avoid cycles we want to be able
因为网络有较长的延迟
has a long speed of light latency and so
所以你完全不会想一次只抓取一个页面
you definitely don't want to fetch pages
除非你想让你的爬虫运行个数年
one at a time unless you want to crawl
如果你同时抓取许多页面的话
to take many years so it pays enormous
你需要使用并行化的方式
keep on increasing the number of pages
持续的增加抓取页面的数量
you fetch in parallel until the
直到达到呑吐极限
throughput you're getting in pages per
也就是每秒你抓取的页面数量
second stops increasing that is running
不在增加为止，也就是并发数的增加
increase the concurrency until you run
这时候也耗尽了网络带宽
out of network capacity so we want to be
所以，我们希望利用并行化的方式抓取
able to launch multiple fetches in
最后一个挑战
parallel and a final challenge which is
有时候也是最难解决的问题
sometimes the hardest thing to solve is
当爬虫运行结束
to know when the crawl is finished
一旦我们已经抓取了所有的页面
and once we've crawled all the pages we
就需要停止爬虫
want to stop and say we're done but we
但是我确实需要写一些代码
actually need to write the code to
来表明：啊哈
realize aha
所有的页面都已经抓取了
we've crawled every single page and for
我已经想出了一些方案
some solutions I've tried figuring out
什么时候结束被证明是
when you're done has turned out to be
最难的一部分
the hardest part all right so my first
所以我的第一个爬虫是一个串行化的爬虫
crawler is this serial crawler here and
顺便说一下，课程表里的 crawler.go 文件中的
by the way this code is available on the
这段代码是可以用的
website under crawler dot go on the schedule
后面你会看到它的
you will look at it this wrist calls a
这个串行爬虫在网页 graph 中
serial crawler it effectively performs a
进行深度优先搜索
depth-first search into the web graph
有件比较有意思的事情
and there is sort of one moderately
它会使用一个 map 类型的变量 fetched
interesting thing about it it keeps this
它只是被当作一个 set 使用
map called fetched which is basically
目的就是为了记住
using as a set in order to remember
它所抓取过的页面
which pages it's crawled and that's like
这是最有意思的部分
the only interesting part of this you
在 18 行你给它一个 URL
give it a URL that at line 18 if it's
如果这个 URL 已经被抓取过它就直接 return
already fetched the URL it just returns
如果没有被抓取过
if it doesn't fetch the URL it first
首先它要把这个 URL 记下
remembers that it is now fetched it
接下来迭代所有的 URL
with the fetcher and then iterates over
然后递归的调用它自己
the URLs in that page and calls itself
对于所有的页面
for every one of those pages and it
它又抓取了很多页面
fetches a bunch of pages after it
在它返回后，我需要意识到
returns I want to be aware you know the
你知道，在抓取实例的外面，需要意识到
outer crawl instance needs to be aware
某些页面是已经抓取过的
that certain pages are already fetched
所以我们十分依赖于
so we depend very much on the fetched
在函数里传递的 fetched 对象
map being passed between the functions
map 使用引用而不是拷贝
by reference instead of by copying so it
所以在底层
so under the hood what must really be
go 把指向map对象的指针
going on here is that go is passing a
传递给
pointer to the map object
而不是（对象）的拷贝
and memory rather than copying rather
有什么问题吗
than copying than that any questions so
这段代码显然没有解决
this code definitely does not solve the
之前提到的问题
problem that was posed right because it
因为它没有并行化的执行 fetch（函数）
doesn't launch parallel parallel fetches
我们需要把 goroutine
now so clue we need to insert goroutines
放在这段代码的某个位置
somewhere in this code right to get
来实现并行的 fetch 让我们假设
parallel fetches so let's suppose just
为了让大家开心一下……
for chuckles dad we just start with the
老爹，让我偷个懒
most lazy thing because why so I'm gonna
为啥我非得这么改代码……
just modify the code to run the
其实就是想把每个 crawl 子调用
subsidiary crawls each in its own
放到各自的 goroutine 里执行
goroutine actually before I do that why
我执行这段代码 给你们看看
don't I run the code just to show you
实际上执行了全部3个crawler
it actually runs all three copies of the
它们都找到了
crawler and they all find exactly the
完全相同的一组网页
same set of webpages so this is the
每个打印出一行
fetched prints a line for each one so
现在我们把crawler
let me now run the subsidiary crawls in
放在各自的goroutine里执行
their own goroutines and run that code
我将看到什么结果
so what am I going to see the hope is to
我们的期望是并行爬取网页
fetch these webpages in parallel for
达到更高的性能 好的
higher performance so okay so you're
你的观点是只会看到一个URL
voting for only seeing one URL and why
为什么
so why is that
对 完全正确
yeah yes that's exactly right you know
它将迅速执行完循环
right through that loop I was gonna
当最开始的那个网页被抓取（第22行）
fetch 1 page when the very first webpage at
紧接着crawl函数就将返回
the crawl function is gonna return and
而且crawl是在main函数里调用的
if it was called from main main what was
几乎可以确定main
exit almost certainly before any of the
会在这些goroutine能做任何事之前退出
goroutines was able to do any work at all
所以我们很可能只会看到第一个网页
so we'll probably just see the first web
我运行它
page and I'm gonna do when I run it
你会看到，这里，在Serial下面
you'll see here under serial that only
唯一被找到的网页
the one web page was found now in fact
由于程序并没有在Serial Crawler结束后退出
since this program doesn't exit after
这些goroutine
the Serial crawler those goroutines are
仍然在运行 实际上 他们打印的输出
still running and they actually print
和后面的crawler例子（的输出）
their output down here interleaved with
混在了一起
the next crawler example but
然而 这段代码 只是在这里加了一个go关键词
nevertheless the codes just adding a go
完全不起作用
here absolutely doesn't work so let's
我们忘掉这段代码 现在我
get rid of that okay so now I want to
想给你们看一种并发风格的crawler
show you a one style of concurrent
我马上会展示其中一个
crawler and I'm presenting to one of
（它）使用了共享数据
them written with shared data shared
共享对象和锁 这是第一个（crawler）
objects and locks it's the first one and
channel 可以让不同的线程之间进行协作
channels in order to coordinate the
现在（要讲的）是共享数据的
different threads so this is the shared
这段代码明显
shared data so this code significantly
最大的不同之处在于
does alright but the huge difference is
它做了两件事
that it does with two things one it does
一是必要的统计 以注意到
the bookkeeping required to notice when
所有爬取完成的时刻
all of the crawls have finished and it
它也会处理共享表格
handles the shared table of which URLs
这个表格记录了已爬取的URL
have been crawled correctly so this code
所以这段代码仍然有URL表格
still has this table of URLs and that's
即 f.fetched
this F dot fetched this F dot fetch
在第43行 这个表格
map at line 43 but this this table is
被所有的crawler线程共享
actually shared by all of the all of the
所有的crawler线程
crawler threads and all the crawler
执行在
threads are making or executing inside
函数 ConcurrentMutex 内 所以我们仍然
ConcurrentMutex and so we still have
有 ConcurrentMutex 的树结构
this sort of tree of ConcurrentMutexes
来探索 web graph 的不同部分
that's exploring different parts of the
但它们中的每一个是被
web graph but each one of them was
被放在各自的goroutine中启动
launched as a as his own goroutine
而不是作为函数调用
instead of as a function call but
但是它们都共享一个状态表
they're all sharing this table of state
记录已爬取URL的表格
this table of fetched URLs because if one
因为如果有个goroutine爬取了一个URL
goroutine fetches a URL we don't want
我们不希望另一个goroutine
another goroutine to accidentally
意外地爬取同一个URL
fetch the same URL and as you can see
你在这里看到 在第42行和第45行
here line 42 and 45 I've surrounded them
我在这段代码前后加上互斥锁
by the mutexes that are required to to
所以这里的危险是
here is that at line 43 a thread is
在第43行 一个线程正在检查URL是否已经被爬取
checking of URLs already been fetched so
两个线程恰好在处理
two threads happen to be following the
同一个URL  两个ConcurrentMutex函数的调用
same URL now two calls to ConcurrentMutex
结果却会看到同一个URL
end up looking at the same URL
原因可能是同一个URL
maybe because that URL was mentioned in
在两个不同的网页都出现过
two different web pages if we didn't
如果我们没有锁
have the lock they'd both access the
它们都将访问表格
math table to see if the threaded and
查看URL是否已经爬取
then already if the URL had been already
在第43行它们都拿到False
fetched and they both get false at line
在第47行 它们都看到already值为False
will both see that I already was false
之后它们都会去爬取这个网页
and then they both go on to fetch the
我们希望第43行和44行（一起）
that we want lines 43 and 44 to be
使用表 我们想要
table between 43 and 44 we we want to
读取当前的内容 每个线程
read the current content each thread
希望能读取当前的表格内容
wants to read the current table contents
并更新 且没有其他线程干扰
and update it without any other thread
这正是锁
interfering and so that's what the locks
为我们做到的事情 对于这里使用锁的策略
are doing for us okay so so actually any
有任何问题吗
questions about the about the locking
strategy here
好 当我们检查表中的URL条目之后
all right once we check the URLs entry
在51行
in the table at line 51 it just crawls
URL被以常见的方式爬取
it just fetches that page in the usual
之后另一个有趣的事情
way and then the other thing interesting
是线程的启动
thing that's going on is the launching
（这个同学的）问题是
of the threads yes so the question is
关于F. 不
what's with the F dot no no the mu it is
在第36行有一个结构体
okay so there's a structure to find out
某种意义上聚集了
line 36 that sort of collects together
所有的不同的东西
all the different stuff that all the
所有我们需要的不同状态 用以运行crawl
different state that we need to run this
这里只有两个对象
crawl and here it's only two objects but
但是可以是更多
you know it could be a lot more and
只是为了方便
they're only grouped together for
并没有什么深层意义
significance the fact that mu and fetched
在同一个结构体里
inside the same structure and
F. 只是一种语法
that F dot is just sort of the syntax
用于取出结构体里的元素
are getting out one of the elements in
我只是刚巧把它们
the structure so I just happened to put
这绝对不是说
absolutely does not mean that go
go把mu和那个结构体联系在一起
associates the mu with that structure or
或是和fetch表联系在一起
with the fetch map or anything it's just
它只是个锁的对象
a lock objects and just has a Lock
（学生的）问题是
so the question is how come in order to
为了传引用，我必须在这里使用*操作符
pass something by reference I had to use
但在前一个例子里
star here where it is when a in the
我们传递了一个map
previous example when we were passing a
我们传递指针
that we're passing a pointer to this
给这个fetchState对象 我们这里要用指针
fetch state object and we want it to be
是因为我们希望
a pointer because we want there to be
所以它们需要一个
same object so they all need a pointer
某种你用来传递指针的语法
the syntax you use for passing a pointer
我们不需要对map这么做
the reason why we didn't have to do it
是因为 虽然
with map is because although it's not
如果你声明一个map类型的变量
declare a variable type map what that is
这个变量是指向堆上数据的指针
is a pointer to some data in the heap so
所以不管怎样，它是个指针
it was a pointer anyway and it's always
它总是以引用形式传递
passed by reference do they you just
你就无需使用*运算符 它（语言）替你做了
don't have to put the star and it does
it for you
所以map是特殊的
so there's they're definitely map is
你不能在语言中定义map
special you cannot define map in the
它必须是语言内置的
language it's it has to be built-in
因为有些古怪的事情
because there's some curious things
好的 好的 我们爬取网页
about it okay good okay so we fetch the
现在我们想要
page now we want to fire off a crawl goroutine
为每一个刚爬取页面中的URL
for each URL mentioned in the
启动一个crawler goroutine
page we just fetch so that's done in
在第56行
line 56 on line 56 just loops over
遍历fetch函数返回的URLs
the URLs that the fetch function
第58行 对每个URL
returned and for each one fires off a
启动一个goroutine
goroutine at line 58 and that lines that
58行的func语法是一个闭包
func syntax in line 58 is a closure or a
或一个匿名函数
sort of immediate function but that func
func关键字声明了一个函数
thing keyword is doing is to clearing a
然后我们调用了这个函数
function right there that we then call
所以 可能 理解（这段代码）的方式是
so the way to read it maybe is
你把一个函数声明成
that if you can declare a function as a
一段数据 先写下func关键字
piece of data as just func you know and
然后给出函数参数
then you give the arguments and then you
之后写出函数体 结束
give the body and that's a clears and so
现在这是一个对象
this is an object now this is like it's
你在声明某种常量对象
a sort of constant object and this is
来运行我们刚声明的这个函数
this function that we declared right
为了让它成为一个goroutine
here and so we in order to make the goroutine
go关键字后面
keywords as you follow it by a function
接函数名 以及要传递的参数
name and arguments you want to pass that
所以我们在这里
function and so we're gonna pass some
传递一些参数 这么做有两个原因
arguments here and there's two reasons
我们这么做
we're doing this well really this one
ConcurrentMutex是
ConcurrentMutex so I ConcurrentMutex is
我们要调用的函数的名字
the name of the function we actually
实际上我们把URL作为参数调用这个函数
want to call with this URL but we want
但我们也想要做一点别的事情
to do a few other things as well so we
所以我们定义这个小辅助函数
define this little helper function that
先调用函数ConcurrentMutex url作为参数
first calls ConcurrentMutex for us with
在ConcurrentMutex
the URL and then after ConcurrentMutex
结束之后 我们做一些
is finished we do something
特殊操作 来帮助我们
special in order to help us wait for all
引入了WaitGroup 第55行的WaitGroup
the the wait group the WaitGroup at
是go语言定义的一个数据结构
line 55 it's a just a data structure defined
用于帮助协作
by go to help with coordination and
就像第57行 你调用WaitGroup.Add()来增加计数器
WaitGroup dot add like line 57 to
调用WaitGroup.Done()
increment the counter and WaitGroup dot done
来减小计数器
to decrement it and then this wait
第63行 这个Wait方法被调用
what this wait method called line 63
等待计数器归零
waits for the counter to get down to
因此WaitGroup是一种
zero so a wait group is a way to wait
用于等待若干事件结束的方式
for a specific number of things to
它在很多不同场景中
finish and it's useful in a bunch of
结束
finish
因为我们对于每个goroutine
because we add one to the wait group
都对WaitGroup加一
for every goroutine we create line 60
第60行 在这个函数的末尾
at the end of this function we've
我们把WaitGroup里的counter减一
declared decrement the counter in the
然后第63行等待
WaitGroup and then line three waits
直到所有的减一操作完成
until all the decrements have finished
我们声明这种函数的原因
and so the reason why we declared this
基本上是为了能够
sort of function was basically to be able
即调用函数ConcurrentMutex 又调用Done
to both call ConcurrentMutex and call
这就是为什么
done that's really why we needed that
我们需要这个函数 （学生的）问题是
function so the question is what if one
如果某个子程序失败 导致done没被调用
of the subroutines fails and doesn't
该怎么办  这是个很好的问题
reach the done line that's a darn good
我不记得
question there is you know if I forget
的错误有哪些
causing the program to fail maybe
可能是除零错误 我不确定
divides by zero I don't know or
或者对null指针解引用
dereferences a null pointer
不太确定 但是有些方式
not sure but there are certainly ways
可以使function失败
for a function to fail and I have the go
goroutine死掉而整个程序不死
routine die without having the program
这对我们是个麻烦
die and that would be a problem for us
所以实际上 正确的方式是
and so really the white right way to I'm
我确定你其实知道这个
sure you had this in mind and asking the
才问这个问题的 正确的写法是
question the right way to write this to
这样写（defer） 以确保 不论goroutine是怎么结束的
be sure that the done call is made no
done都会被调用
matter why this goroutine is finishing
把defer放在这里
would be to put a defer here which means
意味着在包含它的函数结束前调用done.Done()
call done before the surrounding
而且总是会被调用
function finishes and always call it no
不管包含它的函数
matter why this surrounding function is
是以何种原因结束的
finished yes
是的 提问说的是
and yes yeah so the question is how come
为什么两个不同threads对done的调用
two uses of done in different threads
不构成race 答案是
aren't a race yeah so the answer must be
（WaitGroup）内部有互斥锁
that internally dot a WaitGroup has a
或类似的机制
mutex or something like it that each of
每个done的方法会在执行任何指令前先取得锁
done's methods acquires before doing
于是同时
anything else so that simultaneously
调用WaitGroup的方法
calls to a done to a WaitGroups methods
并不构成race
aren't races we could to did a low class
是的 当然 C++ 在C语言中
yeah for certainty C++ and in C you
你可能需要看 pthreads
want to look at something called P
对于C语言，线程由库提供
threads for C threads come in a library
它们不是语言的一部分
they're not really part of the language
叫做 pthreads 它有
called P threads which they have these
非常传统且古老的原语
are extremely traditional and ancient
所有的语言都有
primitives that all languages have yeah
请重复一遍 不在这段代码里
say it again you know not in this code
你可以想象一下WaitGroup如何使用
but you know you could imagine a use of
我的意思是 WaitGroup只是
WaitGroups I mean WaitGroups just
一个计数的东西 是的
count stuff and yeah yeah yeah WaitGroup
WaitGroup并不关心
doesn't really care what you're
你在数什么或者为什么计数 我的意思是
counding or why I mean you know this is
这是最常见的用法
the most common way to see it use you're
你在困惑 为什么u被作为参数
wondering why u is passed as a
传递给58行这个函数
parameter to the function at 58 okay
这里function的规则是
the rules for these for a function like
这里内部函数里的fetcher变量
what is this variable here refer to what
指代的
does the fetcher variable refer to in
内部函数 好吧 它指代
the inner function well it refers it's
和外部函数中fetcher指代的
the same variable as as the fetcher in
是同一个变量
the outer function says just is that
所以当内部函数
variable and so when the inner function
涉及fetcher的地方意味着
refers to fetcher it just means it's
表示它指代的是和这里相同的变量
just referring the same variable as this
同理f也是一样
one here and the same with F f is it's
这里用了它 它就是这个变量
used here it's just is this variable so
所以你可能觉得我们可以摆脱
you might think that we could get rid of
这个u参数
the this u argument that we're passing
就让内部函数完全不含参数
and just have the inner function take no
直接使用
arguments at all but just use the u that
定义在第56行循环里的u
was defined up on line 56 in the loop
因为能让我们少打些字
because save us some typing it turns out
但这样行不通 理由是
not to work and the reason is that the
for循环更新了变量u
for loop updates the variable u so in
所以在for循环的第一次迭代中
the first iteration of the for loop that
变量u包含了某个URL
variable u contains some URL and when
当进入for循环的第二次迭代
you enter the second iteration the for loop
变量的内容
that variable its content are
变成了第二个URL
changed to be the second URL and that
这意味着 我们第一个启动的goroutine
means that the first goroutine that we
看外部
launched that's just looking at the
将看到u中是
we launched would see a different
不同的值
value in the u variable after the outer
（因为）外部函数 已经更新了u
function it updated it and sometimes
有时这正是你们想要的
that's actually what you want so for
希望看到map的变化 但是
wants to see changes to that map but for
对于u 我们不希望看到改变
u we don't want to see changes the
所以我们希望goroutine能够有一份拷贝
want that goroutine to have a copy you
我们也可以那么做
other ways we could have but the way
但是这段代码的
this code happens to do it to produce
给内部函数一个私有拷贝的方式
the copy private to that inner function
是传递URL参数给内部函数 是的
is by passing the URLs in argument yes
是的 如果我们把u的地址传递
yeah if we have passed the address of
是的 事实上
u yeah then it uh it's actually I
我不知道string怎么行得通的
don't know how strings work but it is
变量拷贝 它 是的
copy of the variable and it yeah
你说我们不需要
are you saying we don't need to play
在这段代码中 用这个技巧？
this trick in the code we definitely
我们当然需要这个技巧
need to play this trick in the code and
实际上发生的是 它是
what's going on is this it's so the
（学生的）问题是 既然strings是不可变的
question is Oh strings are immutable
strings是不可变的 是的 那么
strings are immutable right yeah so how
strings是不可变的 那么
kind of strings are immutable how can
外部函数又是怎么改变这个string的呢
the outer function change the string
不该有这个问题 问题并不是
there should be no problem the problem
string被改变了
is not that the string is changed the
问题是变量u
problem is that the variable u is
被改变了 所以当内部函数
changed so the when the inner function
访问一个定义在
mentions a variable that's defined in
里面含有一个字母‘a’
variable that has has a in it and then
然后你把‘B’赋值给那个string变量
you assign B to that string variable
你并不是在重写这个string
you're not overwriting the string
（而是）你改变了这个变量
you're changing the variable to point to
让它指向了一个不同的string
a different string and and because the
由于for循环改变了变量u
for loop changes the u variable to point
它指向了一个不同的string 你懂的
to a different string you know that
这种改变对于内部函数
change to you would be visible inside
是可见的 因此
the inner function and therefore the
内部函数自己需要一个变量的拷贝
inner function needs its own copy of the
variable
好的 但是这正是我们在这段代码里做的
okay but that is what we're doing in
这就是为什么是这段code
this code and that's that is why this
能跑通的原因
code works okay
错误的代码
broken code
但是不幸的
it is unfortunately one that you'll run
你们在lab中会遇到它们
into while doing the labs so you should
所以你们至少应该有意识 这里有个麻烦
be at least aware that there's a problem
当你遇到这个问题时
and when you run into it maybe you can
你可以尝试想弄清楚细节
try to figure out the details okay
这是个很好的问题
that's a great question so so the
如果你有一个内部函数
have an inner function that refers to a
访问定义在外部的变量
variable in the surrounding function but
但是外部函数返回之后
the surrounding function returns what is
内部函数的变量将指向哪里
the inner functions variable referring
go会注意到 go会分析你的内部函数
notices go analyzes your inner functions
或者说闭包
or these are called closures go analyzes
go分析它们 编译器分析它们 aha
them the compiler analyze them says aha
oh 这个闭包 这个函数
oh this disclosure this inner function
使用了外部函数里的变量
is using a variable in the outer
我们实际上会
function we're actually gonna and the
编译器会分配堆内存
compiler will allocate heap memory to
来放这些变量 你懂的
hold the variable the you know the
这些变量的当前的值
current value of the variable and both
两个函数将找到
functions will refer to that that little
堆上的那小片区域 所以
area heap that has the barrel so it
变量不会被分配在栈上
won't be allocated the variable won't be
如你可能预期的
on the stack as you might expect it's
如果编译器看到闭包
moved to the heap if if the compiler
变量会被放到堆上
sees that it's using a closure and then
内部函数还是能够访问到它
inner function can still get at it and
之后垃圾回收器负责
then the garbage collector is
监测最后一个
responsible for noticing that the last
涉及那段堆的函数退出
function to refer to this little piece
返回
of heap that's exited returned and to
并且将它释放 好的
free it only then okay okay
所以WaitGroup WaitGroup可能是
okay so WaitGroup WaitGroup is maybe
（这节课） 更重要的话题
the more important thing here that the
这段代码使用这个技术
technique that this code uses to wait
来等待当前层所有的crawl结束
for all the all this level of crawls to
等待它的直系孩子结束
finish all its direct children and the
当然
finish is the WaitGroup of course
这里有很多这样的WaitGroup
there's many of these WaitGroups one
每次调用ConcurrentMutex函数就有一个（WaitGroup）
per call to ConcurrentMutex each call
ConcurrentMutex等待孩子结束
that ConcurrentMutex just waits for its
然后返回
own children to finish and then returns
好的 回到锁 实际上
okay so back to the lock actually
关于锁还有一个事情 我想要谈
there's one more thing I want to talk
那就是探究 如果我们不加锁
about with a lock and that is to explore
会发生什么
what would happen if we hadn't locked
好的 我认为 你懂的
right I'm claiming oh you know you don't
你不加锁的话，你会遇到race
lock you're gonna get these races you're
你会得到不正确的运行结果
gonna get incorrect execution whatever
问题是：如果我运行这段不加锁的代码
is what happens if I run the code with
我将会看到什么
no locks what am I gonna see so we might
我们可能会看到一个URL打印两次，或者说被爬取两遍
see a url called twice or I fetch
是的 你会想
twice yeah that's yeah that would be the
那将是个错误
error you might expect alright so I'll
我运行无锁的代码
run it without locks and we're looking
我们看ConcurrentMutex
at the ConcurrentMutex the one in the
中间的这段  这次似乎没有
middle this time it doesn't seem to have
爬取任何URL两遍 只有五行
fetched anything twice it's only five
再运行一次 天哪
run again gosh so far genius so maybe
我们可能在浪费时间
we're wasting our time with those locks
是的 似乎永远不有出错
yeah never seems to go wrong I've
实际上我从来没有看到它出错
actually never seen to go wrong so the
虽然如此 代码是错的
code is nevertheless wrong and someday
总有一天程序会失败 好的 问题在于
it will fail okay the problem is that
你懂的
you know this is only a couple of
这里只是几个指令
instructions here and so the chances of
而线程有几百个指令
these two threads which are maybe
两个线程同时执行到这几个指令
hundreds of instructions happening to
且犯错的几率非常低
stumble on this you know the same couple
undefined
of instructions at the same time is
确实 这是
quite low and indeed and and this is a
一个有race bug的代码令人失望的地方
real bummer about buggy code with races
它通常运行良好
is that it usually works just fine but
但当客户在他们的电脑上运行时
it probably won't work when the customer
你懂的 这可能出现在
what do we you know it it can be in
复杂的程序里
complex programs quite difficult to
非常难搞清楚你是不有一个race
figure out if you have a race right and
你可能会 你可能会有一段代码
you might you may have code that just
看起来非常合理
looks completely reasonable that is in
但实际上有某些你未知的race
fact sort of unknown to you using shared
是使用共享变量导致的
variables and the answer is you really
go给我们提供了一个很不错的race探测器
go actually gives us this pretty good
内置于go
race detector built-in to go and you
你应该使用它 如果你把 -race 作为命令行参数
should use it so if you pass the minus race
当你必须让你的go程序
flag when you have to get your go
运行这个race探测器
program and run this race detector which
好的 我将会运行race检测器
well I'll run the race detector and
我们将会看到 它发出了一个错误信息
we'll see so it emits an error message
它已经找到一个race
from us it's found a race and it
实际它上告诉我们
actually tells us exactly where the race
race发生的准确位置 输出里有很多废物
happened so there's a lot of junk in
但是真正关键的是
this output but the really critical
race检测器意识到
thing is that the race detector realize
我们读了一个变量
that we had read a variable that's what
读取的内容是之前写入的
this read is that was previously written
并且（这两个操作）中间
and there was no intervening release and
没有锁的释放和申请
acquire of a lock that's what that's
此外 它告诉我们
what this means furthermore it tells us
行号 所以它告诉我们
the line number so it's told us that the
读取在第43行 写入
read was a line 43 and the write the
之前的写入在第44行 确实
previous write was at line 44 and indeed
我们看代码 读操作在第43行
we look at the code and the read is on
写操作在第44行
line 43 and the write is at line 44 so
这意味着一个线程在第44行
that means that one thread did a write
执行了写入
at line 44 and then without any
之后没有任何锁介入
intervening lock and another thread came
并且之后另一个线程在第43行读取了这个写入的数据
along and read that written data at line
这些就是race探测器寻找的
43 that's basically what the race
基本上对于每一个内存位置
basically for every one of your memory
race探测器
locations the race detector is allocated
都被分配了少量内存
a little bit of memory itself in which
用于跟踪哪些线程
it keeps track of which threads recently
最近读取或者写入了任何内存位置
read or wrote every single memory
然后
location and then when and it also to
它也跟踪
keep tracking keeping track of when
线程申请锁和释放锁
threads acquires or release locks and do
以及别的强制线程
other synchronization activities that it
以非并发形式运行的
knows forces before threads to not
同步活动
run concurrently
如果race探测器看到
and if the race detector ever sees a
有内存位置被写入
ha there was a memory location that was
然后被读取
written and then read with no
而且中间没有锁 它就会报错
intervening lock it'll raise an error
是的 我相信这并不完美
yes I believe it is not perfect yeah I
我必须要思考一下
have to think about it what one
当然一个不完美的情况是
certainly one way it is not perfect is
如果你不执行任何代码
that if you if you don't execute some
那么race探测器不会知道任何事
code the race detector doesn't know
它将不会分析
anything about it so it's not analyzing
它并不是做静态分析
it's not doing static analysis the
race探测器不会看你的源代码
racing detectors not looking at your
不会基于源代码作出判断
source and making decisions based on the
某种程度上 它观察
source it's sort of watching what
一次具体的程序运行
happened at on this particular run of
所以如果这次
the program and so if this particular
具体的程序运行 没有执行
run of the program didn't execute some
某些恰好读写共享数据的代码
code that happens to read or write
那么race探测器不可能知道（有race）
shared data then the race detector will
但这里可能确实有race
never know and there could be a race
这是需要小心的地方
there so that's certainly something to
你懂的 如果你想
watch out for so you know if you're
认真对待race探测器
serious about the race detector you need
你需要设置某种测试装置
to set up sort of testing apparatus that
以确保所有的代码
tries to make sure all all the code is
都被执行 但是这是 非常好
executed but it's it's it's very good
你需要把它用在你的6.824lab中
and you just have to use it for your 824
这是这里的race
labs okay so this is race here and
当然这个race没有真的发生
of course the race didn't actually occur
race探测器没有看到
what the race detector did not see was the
这些敏感代码真的同时执行交织在一起
actual interleaving simultaneous
execution of some sensitive code right
它没有看到两个线程
it didn't see two threads literally
同时执行第43行和第44行
execute lines 43 and 44 at the same time
我们知道
and as we know from having run the
我们已经手动运行了过几次
things by hand that apparently doesn't
显而易见race并没有发生 或者概率很小
happen or only with low probability all it
探测器看到的只是 某时刻有一个写操作
saw was at one point that was a write
很久之后有一个读操作
and then much later there was a
没有锁隔开
read with no intervening lock and so
从那种意义上 它能探测到
in that sense it can sort of
不一定真的会发生的race
detect races that didn't actually happen
或者不会真的导致bug
or didn't really cause bugs okay
好的 最后一个关于这个crawler的问题
okay one final question about this this
它创建了多少个线程
crawler how many threads does it create
最多有多少个并发的线程
yeah and how many concurrent threads
是的 这个crawler的缺陷是
could there be yeah so a defect in this
没有一个明显的
crawler is that there's no obvious bound
同时存在线程的
on the number of simultaneous threads
数量界限 你懂的
that might create you know with the test
在这个测试数据下，只有5个URL
case which only has five URLs big
如果你爬取真实的网络
whoopee but if you're crawling a real
真实的网络 我不确定
real web with you know I don't know are
有数十亿的URL在那儿
there billions of URLs out there maybe
我们当然不希望
not we certainly don't want to be in a
遇到这种情况 crawler可能
position where the crawler might
意外地创建了数十亿计的线程
accidentally create billions of threads
因为 你懂的 几千个线程
because you know thousands of threads
没问题 数十亿计个线程是不行
it's just fine billions of threads it's
它确实创建太多线程
talking about is that it does create too
最好有一种方式
many threads and really ought to have a
可以创建 好比20,000个
way of saying well you can create 20
或100个 或1000个线程
threads or 100 threads or a thousand
但是不会更多
threads but no more so one way to do
一个方式是预先创建
that would be to pre-create a pool a
寻找下一个要爬取的URL
another URL to crawl crawl that URL
而不是为每个URL创建新的线程
rather than creating a new thread for
它的实现方式显著不同
implemented in a significantly
使用了channel
different way using channels instead of
而不是共享内存
shared memory remember on the mutex
回忆之前的版本
call or I just said there is this table
记录URL的表格被所有线程共享
of URLs recorded that's shared
必须加锁
between all the threads has to be
这个版本没有这样一个（共享）的表格
locked this version does not have such a
没有共享内存
table does not share memory and does not
不需要使用锁 好的
need to use locks okay so this one the
它有一个表格
line 86 and it has a table but the
但是这个表格是master函数私有的
table is private to the master function
master函数并不像前一个版本那样
and what the master function is doing is
创建
instead of sort of basically creating a
一棵函数调用树
tree of functions that corresponds to
以对应图结构的搜索
the exploration of the graph which the
这个版本
previous crawler did this one fires off just
为每个URL创建一个goroutine
one u one goroutine per URL that is
但是只由master来创建
fetches and that but it's only the
只有唯一一个master
master only the one master that's
创建这些线程 所以我们没有
creating these threads so we don't have
一个函数的树形结构
a tree of functions creating threads we
我们只有一个master 好的
just have the one master okay so it
它在第88行创建了自己的私有的map
creates its own private map at line 88
记录哪些URL已经爬取
this record what it's fetched and then
然后创建一个channel
it also creates a channel just a single
只有一个channel 所有的worker线程
channel that all of its worker threads
都将通过这个channel沟通
are going to talk to and the idea is
这个思路是 启动一个worker线程
that it's gonna fire up a worker thread
只会通过channel发送恰好一份数据
page will send exactly one item back to
给master
the master on the channel and that item
这份数据包含了这个worker
will be a list of the URLs in the page
从网页上爬取的网页中的URL的列表
that that worker thread fetched so the
master在第89行循环中 从channel中
master sits in a loop we're in line
读取数据
89 is reading entries from the
我们想象
channel and so we have to imagine that
它已经预先启动一些worker
it's started up some workers in advance
现在读取
and now it's reading the information the
这些worker发回的URL列表
URL lists that those workers send back
每当89行拿到一个URL
and each time he gets a URLs is sitting
它遍历
on line 89 it then loops over
这些从爬取的网页中获得的
the URLs in that URL list from a single
URL列表里的URL
page fetch at line 90 and if the URL
如果URL还未被爬取，它将在第94行
hasn't already been fetched it fires off
启动一个新的worker去爬取那个URL
a new worker at line 94 to fetch that
我们看worker代码
URL and if we look at the worker code
第77行 从第77行开始 大概是说
on line starting on line 77 basically calls
调用fetcher 然后第80行，82行
his fetcher and then sends a message on
发送信息给channel
the channel at line 80 or 82 saying
这是爬取的网页中的URLs
here's the URLs in the page they fetched
注意到
and notice that now that the maybe
可能有趣的事情是
interesting thing about this is that the
worker线程不共享任何对象
worker threads don't share any objects
worker和master之间
there's no shared object between the
也不共享任何对象
workers and the master so we don't have
所以我们不必担心锁
to worry about locking we don't have to
我们不必担心race
worry about races instead this is a
这是通信的例子
example of sort of communicating
而不是通过
information instead of getting at it
共享内存 是的
through shared memory yes
是的 可以观察到
yeah yeah so the observation is that the
代码看上去好像 但是worker是
code appears but the workers are the
可以观察到 worker在改变channel
observation is the workers are modifying
同时master在读channel
ch while the master is reading it and
go的作者不会希望
that's not the way the go authors would
你们这样理解
like you to think about this the way
他们希望你这么思考
they want you to think about this is
这完全合法 channel毫无压力
that's perfectly legal the channel is
有一个互斥锁
channel has a mutex in it and the
使用了互斥锁
the channels internal data to ensure
来保证
that it doesn't actually have any
实际上没有任何race 是的
races in it but yeah channels are sort
channel被保护了起来 免受并发风险
of protected against concurrency and
你可以在不同的线程中
you're allowed to use them concurrently
并发地使用它 是的
from different threads yes
通过channel接收 是的
over the channel receive yes
我们不需要关闭channel
we don't need to close the channel I
我的意思是 好吧 这个break语句
mean okay the the break statement is
当crawl完全结束
about when the crawl has completely
我们爬取了每个URL
finished and we fetched every single URL
发生的事情是
right because hey what's going on is the
master持续  我的意思是 这个n
master is keeping I mean this n value is
是私有的 每当master
private value and a master every time it
启动一个worker 会增加n
fires off a worker increments the n
每个启动的worker
though every worker it starts sends
发送恰好一个东西到channel上
exactly one item on the channel and so
所以每次master从channel读取一个
every time the master reads an item off
就能知道 一个worker
the channel it knows that one of his
已经结束 当worker数目
workers is finished and when the number
当所有worker的数目降为0
of outstanding workers goes to zero then
之后唯一引用channel的
the only reference to the channel is
是master函数 或者
from the master or from oh really from
是调用master的代码
the code that calls the master and so
垃圾回收器很快看到
the garbage collector will very soon see
这个channel没有被引用
that the channel has no references to it
将会释放这个channel
and will free the channel so in this
关闭channel
close channels
问题说的是
so the question is alright so you can
看第106行 在调用master之前
see at line 106 before calling master
并发channel某种程度启动了一个
concurrent channel sort of fires up one
把一个URL塞进了channel
shoves one URL into the channel and it's
这样开始整个流程
to sort of get the whole thing started
从channel读取数据
reading from the channel line 89 so
所以最开始channel中要有数据
there better be something in the channel
否则89行将永远阻塞
otherwise line 89 would block forever so
如果没有107行的代码
if it weren't for that little code at
89行将block在读channel上
line 107 the for loop at 89 would block
一个观察是 天哪 如果
observation is gosh you know wouldn't it
写出的代码
be nice to be able to write code that
能够注意到
would be able to notice if there's
是否有东西在等待channel 就好了
nothing waiting on the channel and you
如果你去看select语句 你可以做到
can if you look up the Select statement
让你免于block 继续执行
allows you to proceed to not block if
如果没有等待在channel
something if there's nothing waiting on
the channel
因为worker没有结束 好的 抱歉
because the worker aren't finish okay sorry
对于第一个问题 我觉得
to the first question is there I think
你真正担心的是
what you're really worried about is
我们是否真的能够并行启动
whether we're actually able to launch
最开始的第一个fetch不会并行
parallel so the very first fetch won't be
因为
in parallel because there's an exit
不 不 不 for循环在第89行等待
no no no the for-loop waits in at line 89
89行的for loop
that's not okay that for loop at line 89
并不是 遍历当前channel的内容
is does not just loop over the current
然后退出
contents of the channel and then quit
89行的for循环将会读
that is the for loop at 89 is going to
它可以永不退出
read it may never exit but it's gonna
它将一直等待
read it's just going to keep waiting
直到有东西出现在channel中
until something shows up in the channel
所以 如果没有第99行的break
so if you don't hit the break at line 99
for循环不会被结束 是的 好
the for loop won't exit yeah alright I'm
恐怕我们时间到了 我们会继续
afraid we're out of time we'll continue
事实上我们的助教安排了一场展示
this actually we have a presentation
在那儿会聊更多关于go的话题
scheduled by the TAs which will talk more about go